Finding Aid for Charles Thomas Jr. Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Thomas Jr. Papers 1965-1994, 1968-1980
Thomas, Charles, 1937-1994.
1 oversized folder UAm
4 linear feet
961 Aa UAm
Ann Arbor, Michigan civil rights activist known for his confrontational style and advocate of black economic development, welfare rights, affordable housing and other causes, and a founder of the Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League. Papers, primarily documenting his work with the WCBEDL, include correspondence, scrapbooks, trial transcripts, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 8338 ) was donated by Darcy H. Thomas and Francine Fein in March 1995.
The collection is open for research.
Charles Thomas, Jr., was born on November 29, 1937, in Wilson, Arkansas. He died on August 2, 1994 in Ann Arbor, Michigan at the age of 56.
When Thomas was young, his family moved to Ypsilanti. He never finished high school, opting instead for a career in the military, which started at age 14 when an overzealous recruiter let him join the Army. Thomas was sent to the Korean conflict, but was discharged when his true age was revealed.
In 1955, Thomas was old enough to join the Marines, with whom he remained until 1967 when he retired with the rank of sergeant. Returning to Ann Arbor, Thomas soon became heavily involved in the Civil Rights movement. His activities, including some brushes with the law, led to the monitoring of his actions by the local and state authorities. From this time until the mid-1970s, the Michigan State Police collected information about Thomas, which became part of the so-called "Red Squad Files." Although primarily concerned with the rights of African-Americans, Thomas was active in any struggle in which he perceived oppression. He was the chairman of the Committee to Recall [Washtenaw County] Sheriff [Douglas] Harvey in 1969, and a supporter of the Welfare Rights Organization.
Thomas was known for his confrontational style. In 1970, he "took over" several church services in primarily white congregations to read the "Black Manifesto", which demanded financial reparations to blacks from the white community in payment for racial oppression. When a church failed to respond to his demands, Thomas would stage a sit-in, joined by members of the Welfare Rights Organization and the newly formed Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League (WCBEDL). Despite initial resistance, the sit-ins were instrumental in the creation of the Inter-Faith Coalition of Congregations, which provided the main source of funding for WCBEDL.
WCBEDL was a non-profit organization located at 340 Depot Street in Ann Arbor. The WCBEDL-sponsored Community Development Center, built in part by BEDL construction students, was equipped with TV cameras, sound equipment, a dark room, and computers. Young people were trained in computer use and repair as well as photography, journalism, and FCC license requirements. WCBEDL sponsored scholarships for students to attend Community High School and Washtenaw Community College. In the mid-1970s, Thomas began an after-school and summer enrichment program, providing recreational opportunities for young people and exposing them to cultural centers and the arts. For his dedication to minority youth, Thomas received commendations from the Huron Valley Association of Black Social Workers in 1973, and from the Ann Arbor City Council in 1977.
In addition to his work at WCBEDL, Thomas was interested in providing affordable housing to Washtenaw County residents. He was one of the first in the community to explore passive solar housing, and was active in several minority construction industry associations.
After Thomas died in 1994, a scholarship for African-American youth was established in his name at Washtenaw Community College.
The Charles Thomas, Jr. papers relate mainly to the activities of WCBEDL, the organization founded by Thomas in 1970. Materials in the collection include scrapbooks, trial transcripts, newsclippings, photographs, and correspondence, (including four letters from Coretta Scott King located in the WCBEDL correspondence file).
The Charles Thomas, Jr. papers are divided into the following four series:
Personal/Biographical, ca. mid 1960s-1994 (1.3 linear ft.)
Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League (WCBEDL) Files, 1970-1990 (2 linear ft.)
Topical Files, ca. 1960s-1980s (0.5 linear ft.)
Photographs, ca. late-1960s-1970s (0.2 linear ft.)
Form and Genre:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Thomas, Charles, 1937-1994.; Afro-American civil rights workers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Civil rights movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Radicalism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scrapbooks.; University of Michigan--Students.; Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials
Thomas, Charles, 1937-1994.; Afro-American civil rights workers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Civil rights movements--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Radicalism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scrapbooks.; University of Michigan--Students.; Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Thomas, Charles, 1937-1994.; Sound recordings.
- Personal/Biographical circa mid 1960s-1994, 1.3 linear feet
  The papers in the Personal/Biographical File series are predominantly comprised of Charles Thomas' personal scrapbooks and documentation of his various legal battles. Thomas' role in the formation of WCBEDL, his involvement in local church sit-ins, and in political and social causes were well documented in local newspapers. These newsclippings comprise the bulk of the scrapbooks, which date mainly from the late 1960s and early 1970s. Thomas' legal battles are also well documented, with newsclippings, trial transcripts, court rulings, and materials gathered by Thomas to support his defense. Scattered throughout the "Legal Proceedings" files are Thomas' personal notes of the cases. From these, a researcher may be able to map out Thomas' legal strategies Of special interest is the "Red Squad Files" folder, containing copies of covert investigations of Thomas by state and local police. This series also contains a small personal correspondence folder, and biographical information such as birth and death certificates and obituaries. Researchers may also want to look in the Photographs series for photographs taken during the Black Action Movement (BAM) protest in March 1970.
  - Biographical Information, including birth and death certificates, obituaries, and a sound recording of Thomas' memorial service (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, circa mid 1960s-1988 (Box 1)
  - First Presbyterian Church Membership, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Legal Proceedings
    - Black Action Movement (BAM) trial
      - General 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      - Dismissal of case November 13, 1973 (Box 1)
      - Newsclippings, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Gun Charge, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Legal Cases, including church trespassing charges, 1968-early 1970s (Box 1)
    - Trial Transcripts
      - State of Michigan vs. Charles Thomas, Jr., January 26, 1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - State of Michigan vs. Hank Bryant and Charles Thomas, Jr., February 18, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Military Records, 1960-1968 (Box 1)
    - Red Squad Files, (photocopy), circa 1960s-mid 1970s (Box 1)
    - Scrapbooks
      - circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970 (Box 1)
      - 1971 (Box 2)
      - 1972 (Box 2)
      - 1973, 1980 (Box 2)
- Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League (WCBEDL) Files 1970-1990, 2 linear feet
  The Washtenaw County Black Economic Development League (WCBEDL) Files series is the heart of this collection. Charles Thomas devoted the last 25 years of his life to WCBEDL, which provided financial support for the educational goals of the area's black youth, as well as serving as a training center in the areas of communication, electronics, and construction. Local churches provided most of the funding for WCBEDL, but their support was hard won. The folders in the "Church Relations" sub-series contain a copy of the "Black Manifesto", describe area congregations' reactions to Thomas' reading of it, the subsequent sit-ins, and the formation of the Inter-Faith Coalition of Congregations (IFCC). Researchers should also check the "Funding Sources" folders for other sources of funding. An overview of classes offered at WCBEDL is in the "Classes" files, including folders on the after-school and summer youth programs. Recipients of scholarships and their progress reports are in the "Community High School" and " Washtenaw Community College" sub-series. Multimedia classes offered to Community High students are in the "Community Resources Program" folders within the " Community High School" file. WCBEDL was also interested in the construction of energy-efficient family living spaces, as documented in the "Community Development Center" and "Construction Projects" files. The "Board of Directors" files, which contain correspondence and meeting minutes, are an excellent way to document the activities of WCBEDL, although there are no records from the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, 1970, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Black Music Project, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors
    - Correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box 2)
    - Initial Actions 1970 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1970-1977, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Bulletin Board System, circa late 1980s (Box 2)
  - Certificate of Appreciation from Huron Valley Association of Black Social Workers, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Charitable Trust Questionnaire, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Church Relations
    - Ann Arbor Area Church Sit-Ins, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Black Manifesto and Church Reaction 1969 (Box 2)
    - Catholic
      - Local 1970-1972 (Box 2)
      - State and National 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Interfaith Coalition of Congregations (IFCC)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1975, 1994 (Box 2)
      - General 1970-1989 (Box 2)
      - Newsletter, 1974-1975, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Lutheran
      - Local and National 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    - Methodist
      - Local 1972-1978 (Box 2)
      - National 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Churches, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    - Presbyterian
      - Black Presbyterians United, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Guest Speaker Park United Presbyterian, July 28, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Local 1971-1975 (Box 2)
      - National 1972-1977 (Box 2)
      - Presbytery of Detroit, 1972-1978 (Box 2)
      - Self-Development Validating Committee
        - Bylaws, 1974 (Box 2)
        - General 1970-1977 (Box 2)
        - Meeting Minutes, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
        - WCBEDL Progress Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - Southern Michigan Presbytery, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Cinderella (television play produced by WCBEDL), circa 1980s (Box 2)
  - Classes
    - Audio Visual Applications, circa 1980s (Box 2)
    - CB Radio Course, circa 1976 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Introduction to Computers, circa 1980s (Box 2)
    - Journalism and Photojournalism 1974 (Box 2)
    - Learning Resistor Color Code, A Study Guide, circa 1980s (Box 2)
    - Multimedia and Construction Class Student List Fall 1984 (Box 2)
    - Multi-Media Center
      - General 1974-1976 (Box 2)
      - FCC Licensing Course, 2nd Class, 1975 (Box 2)
      - Radio Operating Licensing circa 1970s (Box 2)
      - Studio Equipment Operation circa 1970s (Box 2)
      - Television Production Script 1974 (Box 2)
    - Photography, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Photography Contest, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Student Reports circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
    - Youth Development Program
      - After School Program, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
      - Progress Report 1977 (Box 3)
      - Summer Program, 1977, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Community Development Center (CDC)
      - American Institute of Architects clippings, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - Articles of Incorporation, 1974 (Box 3)
      - CDRS Proposals 1974, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Non-Profit Reports 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Community High School
      - Community Resources Program
        - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
        - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1974, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Financial Support for Students 1973-1975 (Box 3)
      - Student Progress Reports 1973-1977 (Box 3)
    - Computer-Assisted Instruction Task Force Reports, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Construction Projects
      - Passive Solar Apartment Building, 1976-1990, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, A-Z (Box 3)
      (including copies of four letters from Coretta Scott King)
    - Fashion Show, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Financial Statement, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Funding Sources
      - Churches and Other Religious Institutions, 1978-1992 (Box 3)
      - Foundations, 1972-1992 (Box 3)
      - Individual Donors, 1978, 1987 (Box 3)
      - IFCC 1980-1992 (Box 3)
    - Insurance Policy for WCBEDL 1978 (Box 3)
    - Inventory of Equipment 1974 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Annual Report for Non-Profit Corporations 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Multi-Media Center Dedication 1973 (Box 3)
    - Newsclippings
      - 1970-1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973-1980 (Box 3)
    - News Releases, 1970-1974 and undated (Box 3)
    - Perspective on Habitable Inner Cities (conference) 1985 (Box 3)
    - Progress Reports 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Progress Reports 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Revenue Sharing Workshop (sponsored by WCBEDL) 1973 (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw Community College
      - Architectonics Program
        - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3)
        - General 1968, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Charles Thomas Jr. Scholarship, 1995 (Box 4)
      - Program Descriptions 1973-1975 (Box 4)
      - Scholarship
        - Applications 1973-1974 (Box 4)
        - Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 4)
        - Recipients 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - " WCBEDL News", 1985-1989 (Box 4)
    - WCBEDL Objectives and Program Descriptions circa early 1970s (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw County Construction Industry Affirmative Action Program
      - Affirmative Action Reporter 1974-1976 (Box 4)
      - Bylaws, circa early 1970s (Box 4)
      - Status Reports 1973-1976 (Box 4)
      - WCBEDL Scholarships circa early 1970s (Box 4)
- Topical Files circa 1960s-1980s, 0.5 linear feet
  Charles Thomas' miscellaneous interests and activities are documented in the Topical Files series. This series includes the records of The Medina, an ethnic clothing and gift shop owned by Thomas and his wife, Patricia, in the mid-1960s. There is a large file on the activities of Washtenaw County Sheriff; Douglas Harvey. In 1972, Thomas co-taught a college-level class called Community Control, as part of the Program for Education and Social Change (PESC). Further information in PESC can be found in the "PESC" folder and the " John Sinclair and the White Panther Party" folder. Thomas' theater involvement is described in the " Ann Arbor Black Theatre" folder.
  Newsclippings on subjects that interested Thomas comprise the bulk of this series, and topics include African issues, blacks in the news, racial and women's issues, a Washtenaw County dental care study, community access television, and the Model Cities program. Thomas' involvement with various committees and associations is also documented in this series.
  - African Issues, circa 1980s (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Black Theatre, 1970s and undated (Box 4)
  - Association of Black Social Workers, 1973-1974 and undated (Box 4)
  - Black Panthers, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Black-Jewish Relations, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Blacks in the News, 1963-1972 (Box 4)
  - Byrd, David (Architectonics Program and County Commissioner) Election, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
  - Center for Afro-American Studies, University of Michigan, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Committee for New Understandings of Justice, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Community Access TV (CATV), Ann Arbor, 1970, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Community Development Revenue Sharing Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Cruse, Harold, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Dental Care Study, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Direct Action Committee Report, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Greater Philadelphia Black Economic Development Conference, circa 1970s (Box 4)
  - Harvey, Douglas (Washtenaw County Sheriff)
    - Ann Arbor Area Murders, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Committee to Recall Sheriff Harvey, 1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Newsclippings, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - South University Demonstrations, 1969 (Box 4)
  - King, Martin Luther, Birthday Celebrations, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Loving, Alvin, Sculpture, Detroit, 1971 (Box 4)
  - The Medina
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Legal Papers, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Supply Catalogs and Invoices circa mid 1960s (Box 4)
  - Minority Business Development Group, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Model Cities Program
    - General 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Newsclippings, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
  - National Black Media Coalition, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - North Central Property Owner's Association, 1974, 1976 and undated (Box 4)
  - Organized Religion, 1965, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - Patent Search for Stud-Spacer (invention of Johnnie Clark, WCBEDL student), 1973 (Box 4)
  - Peace Neighborhood Center, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Program for Education and Social Change (PESC), 1972 (Box 4)
  - Public Defender Program, Washtenaw County, 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Self-Determination Nation and Class (a community forum) circa mid 1970s (Box 4)
  - Sinclair, John, and the White Panther Party, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
  - St. Joseph Hospital Relocation, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - War Reparations Legislation, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw County Black Contractors and Tradesmen Association, Inc., 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw County Minority Business Enterprise Steering Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw County Print Cooperative, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Welfare Rights Organization (WRO), 1969-1971 (Box 4)
  - Women's Issues, 1972-1974 and undated (Box 4)
- Photographs, circa late 1960s-1970s, 0.2 linear feet
  Materials in the Photographs series range from photos of Thomas and his wife, to performance photos from Ann Arbor Black Theatre productions, to WCBEDL activities, to the March 1970 BAM protest. Most are black and white photographs.
  - Black Action Movement (BAM) Protest, March 17, 1970, 10 developed Negative strips (Box 4)
  - Black Theatre Productions, circa 1969, 5 photographs black and white (Box 4)
    (various actors and stage shots)
  - Community Development Center (CDC), circa early 1970s, 11 photographs (in 2 folders) black and white (Box 4)
    (on mat board)
  - Media Operators and WCBEDL circa 1980s, 2 photographs black and white (Box 4)
  - Stringfellow, William, circa early 1970s, 3 photographs black and white (Folder 1)
    (located in UAm)
  - Thomas, Charles Jr., circa late 1960s-early 1970s, 1 photograph black and white (Box 4)
  - Thomas, Patricia, circa mid 1960s, 7 photographs black and white (Box 4)
  - Upland Hills Ecological Awareness Center, undated, 19 photographs color (Box 4)